So you really need to understand your
whole set of metrics and how do they all
work together because most of the cases
something goes up and something goes
down and you need to make sure you know
what is going on.
>> Hello, I'm your host David Bernard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
Cat's state of subscription apps report.
Each episode in this series will explore
one crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Sarah Grana,
who works on revenue strategy at
Musician. On the podcast, I talk with
Sarah about the cost of not tracking
your experiments and decisions, how
refunds and chargebacks quietly erase
your paywall wins, and why stacking AB
test wins should compound your growth,
but almost never does. Hey Sarah, thanks
so much for joining me on the podcast
today.
>> Thanks for having me, David.
>> So you spent almost seven years at Babel
and recently transitioned to Musician.
And one of the the things you told me
when we were preparing for this was that
the first thing you did at Musician was
you asked like where's your log of
experiments? Where's your log of
business decisions? I don't think a lot
of companies keep that kind of record.
[laughter]
So why was that the first thing you
asked? and and how do you recommend
doing that?
>> So when um I start a company and also
when I started at bubble in my role in
revenue strategy I really look at okay
what is the map of our revenue over the
years. So from your revenue will come
from subscription business. You can
either get money from people that never
had a subscription and start a new
subscription. People that upgraded from
a subscription to another, people that
renew a subscription or people that used
to have subscription then turn and then
came back. So like these four buckets,
you have like these four buckets. Having
the history of how these four buckets
evolve can also tell you a lot. So when
sometimes you cannot find experiments or
what not you can see, oh I see that from
February 23 all of a sudden the new
subscriber revenue went really you know
like really big like what happened and
they're like oh yeah this is when we
started the lifetime subscription or I
you know like this type of things. So
sometimes it's about finding yeah it's
great if they have a log and then you
can go through experiments but you need
to differentiate okay what is what is
important versus not because sometimes
you run like some companies run a lot of
experiments so it's not really useful to
go through all of it so I would also
recommend let's map the revenue
understand what are the big difference
that you see and then try to map okay
something happened here what happened
and then that would tell you a lot about
the history and how things work together
also in in that particular company or
sector.
>> How would you recommend actually
tracking that or like in your ideal
state? Is that just in a notion doc and
a Google doc or is it in a spreadsheet
and like the revenue changes that happen
like what's the ideal state of something
like that look like? basically the
revenue bucket so to say to me it's like
Excel like I would track in Excel like
how how are moving and then from that
maybe have a little presentation for me
or like then to share and then you map
okay here you know this line this
happened because of this thing and then
you can like link to whatever data taker
or whatever documentation that is the
company or you can put like within the
same Excel file if you stay in Excel the
links of what happened when but yeah I'm
I mean I'm a bit of an Excel person. But
yeah, like everyone needs to find their
own way
>> when you're trying to optimize
conversion, retention, when you're
working on, as you do, revenue strategy
at a company. All these little things
add up to become the product in a way
that is hard to untangle from each
other. And so having this record means
that, you know, when you ran this
experiment, you can then go back and
look at that cohort. Did it, you know,
turn at a higher rate? Did they engage
in the app in a different rate? How did
they engage in the app differently? And
so all of that leads to kind of making
better decisions over the long haul and
being able to look back historically and
understand those decisions and maybe
retest some of the assumptions from the
past. But one of the big things is
conversion over optimization. I think a
lot of apps are falling into this trap
these days of getting too focused on
earlyFunnel metrics at the expense of
downfunnel metrics. So what are some of
the pitfalls you've seen in that?
>> I think there's two major things that I
keep seeing over and over again. One of
them is this not letting enough time for
the cohort to evolve and see what
happens later. Right. What you mentioned
like what happens with the renewal rates
like okay we have a price increase. Oh
great, you know we did amazing. We
rolled this and then six months later
you look at the cohort and say oh
actually the control group actually is
performing better than the test group
because they are you know renew more. So
one of them is like this not looking you
know like giving the time sometimes it's
fine to roll out right it's fine you
have a win you roll but then look back
right and then the second one is within
the same moment in time like the same
snippet in time but not looking at the
right metrics like there's sometimes
that we forget to look at some metrics I
give like a really clear example
sometimes with a winback win back
campaign okay or like people that cancel
their auto renewal okay when They do
that, we're going to send an offer,
right? Okay, they cancel to renew. We
send an offer because then maybe we get
them back. Okay, great. We do this great
amazing numbers. Okay, you look a bit
more deep and you realize, oh, a lot of
people are cancel, you know, like
putting the outre at the beginning and
what they're doing is they're asking for
a refund and then they're getting the
offer. So, you are actually like net
negative. So I think that's also
something that tends to happen
especially with refunds and chargebacks
and because people tend to forget about
those like they never happen and um yeah
you might be even without waiting in
time you might be messing up with your
system. So you really need to understand
your whole set of metrics and how do
they all work together because most of
the cases something goes up and
something goes down and you need to make
sure you know what is going on. I hear
this all the time with price testing
where you double the price and you
exactly match the revenue. So conversion
cuts in half. Sometimes you'll get that
win where you double the price and you
do get a 25% lift in average revenue per
user or something like that. But you
always got to be looking for those
downstream things. Like you said, one
thing goes up, another goes down. You
know, when you look at the entire life
cycle of a subscriber, any one movement
here can have downstream effects if
you're not really carefully looking for
it. And I think we're just in this mode
as an industry of chasing payback as
quickly as possible. And sometimes it's
like it's just a business decision you
have to make. you have to make that
decision of like we're going to
sacrifice long-term revenue for being
able to hit that rorowaz at day whatever
7 30 90 whatever you're targeting but I
think what's really important and what
you're hinting at is like you got to
know what you're sacrificing you got to
know as you push this number up what
number is going down and are you willing
to make that trade because a lot of
times people aren't tracking those
downfunnel numbers and don't know the
trade they're making. What are some of
the specific examples you've seen of
that kind of overoptimization and and
how how it does impact the long term? It
happens also a lot when introducing new
plans like when you didn't have the
yearly subscription or when you didn't
have the lif I mean lifetime is a huge
example because the value that you get
from the get-go like it's really high
and then every time like every time you
do a test like lifetime versus something
else like always the something else is
going to lose because people are not
looking at what is the LTV of that
something else right like if they would
have bought a tour subscription they are
not bringing you the the €100 they are
bringing you like €300 so don't compare
it with the you know 250 compared to 300
um and things like that. So I think like
every time there's like a new plan that
always like people please look at the
lifetime value that this plan would have
had. And then another thing that um
happened I said before like a lot like
refunds and chargeback is something that
people tend to forget about. So if you
are introducing a new payment method and
things like this also like especially
like how look at those metrics look what
is happening there. any other specific
places you think people should be paying
especially close attention to? I know,
you know, payw wall optimization is a
huge thing and I've been frankly
surprised at how big of moves folks have
been able to see on the payw wall. Like
over this past year, one of the like
really big paywall optimization things
that that people have been doing is
having a toggle to enable the free
trial. So by default, you don't have a
free trial. you, you know, tap a button
or slide a slider and it enables a free
trial. And now Apple has started to
reject some of that. So, I don't know if
that's going to be something that is
allowed long term, but I've been shocked
at like, you know, what a big lift that
can have. But again, I haven't talked to
folks who looked at that cohort 6
months, 12 months down the line. I mean,
we're just now I mean, I think that that
started about 12 months ago, so you're
going to start seeing those cohorts
maturing. any things like other things
like that that you've seen that that
that you saw very specifically lead to
downfunnel problems? Sometimes it's not
so much what we said like downfalling
problem and more like you are just
putting the revenue at the beginning
right is just that more revenue than at
the end or not but one thing that
happens that is really clear like with
churn people usually tend to just think
churn is a product thing like churn is a
product problem but most of the time I
not most of the time let's say most of
the time but a lot of the time like the
commercial strategy that you have what
people buy when they buy it and which
price they buy it are going to have such
an enormous impact on your renewals and
extensions and what happens is that
people like in the u marketing side they
don't really you know see in the index
and then the product side they also
don't have a view on what is happening
at the beginning of the funnel in a way
for example something that I think is
going to happen right now is we have now
the web check out right in iOS you can
send people to buy in web what I've seen
in different companies is the web
renewal rates are significant ificantly
higher than the up rate. So what is
going to happen now is a lot of teams a
lot of product teams are going to be
like wow like our product is amazing we
have increased our you know renewals by
whatever 20%. If they were to slice from
what is a cohort of users that bought
you know natively in app what is the
cohort of users that bought through web
maybe the renewal rates are flat and
what just happen is you are acquiring
users through other means. The same can
be said of course for the subscription
plans like if you have like your share
of users that by one month subscription
is bigger or like growth for whatever
reason your renewals are also going to
get better. if you look at the to
overall number. So I think when you're
looking at data like cohort of the
different users what they bought when
they bought it if discounted or not
discounted is also another clear example
like sometimes you do a discount you
bring a lot of revenue but then those
users they are not going to renew or
sometimes you do a price increase you
bring more revenue because your
conversion goes down but not as much as
your as the price increase goes up but
then those users you have like less pool
to upgrade users and things like this.
So there's a lot of a lot of um
different colors to this problem.
>> So what are the specific metrics and
ways you dive into the data to better
understand that? Are you looking at both
subscription retention and usage
retention of very specific features like
how are you watching that entire funnel?
What's your preferred way to look at it?
What are the metrics you most look at?
>> So what is more most important to me is
which plan did they buy discounted or
not? and where like you know web versus
app. Then sometimes in some and this is
something that you need to like look for
your company right sometimes the
marketing channel might make up for
different users and cohorts right so
understand what are the different one
and once you have that then you just
look at that you just look at that
cohort and then if you see that the
cohort is going up or down you know okay
probably it's a product thing what
usually happens is that this h the share
for those different cohorts is changing
over time and this is what bringing you
the fluctuation on renewal rates. It
might be different when you're um yeah
when you're doing a specific experiment,
you know, that might change that. But I
think it's really always good to look at
what are those things that make a
difference that are upper funnel as
upper funnel as it gets so to say and
then uh look for that. And then when it
comes to when I'm looking at a test that
I do in the pay wall, what not then I'm
looking at revenue per user of course,
but then I'm also having a look always
on preback. So I always wait like a
couple of weeks what is happening there
because that's like an immediate effect
that you can see and then always after
some months recheck the cohort you know
like what has happened with these
people. Sometimes it's a bit frustrating
because you have the majority of your
users buying a 12 month subscription. So
you won't see it until later on but
maybe there's something that you can do
if you see that the one month behaving
in a particular way. Maybe you can
assume that the same would happen for
the 12 months. You can also look when
you have the result make some scenarios
of renewal rates of those different you
know if the one month was was to renew
at this as this you know like 10% less
or 5% more whatever you want based on
the result of your test what would
happen and then you can know once you
know like you have some like really easy
way to check in a way like in a sense
like you can you keep an eye okay if it
goes below 10 then I know we are in
trouble I know that probably the the
winner is actually the loser And this
gets back to the what we started with
was keeping a detailed history. Is that
when you do run an experiment, do you
set like an alarm like you know three
months from now?
>> Yeah. Yeah. My Google calendar up there
has this experiment recheck with my like
the data analyst. Yeah.
>> Gotcha. So you are looking back at at
specific intervals and do you do that
for I guess you wouldn't do that for
every test. What's the criteria for the
things that you're most career to look
back on? I think like anything that is
price changes I really care about
because for example if it's about oh the
layout is different or like the copy is
different then sure maybe there's a
different in renewal by why would it
right like so there's certain things
that like probably not so I don't know
like you shouldn't be spending a lot of
time the thing is also the more you do
it the easier it gets in a way it's just
like a another part of the of the
analysis so to say it's already set up
that way. So you have already a cohort
it's like okay you pull back okay yeah
here and sometimes it's even with some
tools is even there that you can just
recheck this test how it perform so it
doesn't need to be like really time
consuming but usually everything
everything that is with price or
discounting or thing like this I would
always uh recheck after yeah depending
on what we are selling you know like 3
months 6 months and then if you have to
wait a year is yeah
>> it seems like too maybe the the priority
would
to make sure you're checking back on the
things that made the biggest move. So
maybe there was a copy change on the
payw wall button that that did a 25%
lift, which is sounds crazy, but it
happens sometimes where you have these
like crazy lifts. And so maybe those
kind of things would also kind of fall
into that bucket of like anything that
made a surprisingly big lift. Mark that
one to go back on because
>> especially if then you are not seeing
because something that happens a lot is
oh we have all these experiments all
positive but then when you're looking at
the numbers you know you're still flat
you're still improve but not that much.
So Especially if you see that then it's
time it's more time to recheck like
actually I would say if you see that the
growth of your company follows all your
AB test increases then it's less of a
you know like red flag maybe you're like
oh maybe you don't need to retest you
seem to be doing fine I think that
because I think a lot of the times we're
like yeah all this like you know I look
all the list of you know experiments
with like 5% 10% I'm like but wait a
second like what why we are not growing
you know like 30% year on year if we
have all these wins and I think this
happens also like with product like with
with um you know like a new feature what
not yeah this lift this lift but then
when you look over time it's not really
holding together so I think there's also
like I don't know why it happens right
but um there's this like mismatch
between what your AB tests are telling
you and what the long-term effects is
telling you That is that is such a great
point. It's like you can stack all these
wins. Oh, we got 10% higher completion
in the onboarding step. Oh, we got 15%.
>> And it should compound. It should even
compound. So, it should be even like way
more than than that. And it's not. So,
yeah,
>> tracking and and u making sense of all
this is such a challenge, but that's why
you need to do it. You're not actually
getting that 10% increase if you're not
actually getting that [laughter] 10%
increase. and you're never going to know
if you do these experiments in isolation
and aren't tracking everything. So, it
was so fun to chat with you about all of
this. Thank you so much for coming on
the podcast. Anything else you wanted to
share as we're wrapping up? I know
you've just started this new role at
Musician. Any uh job listings you want
to shout out or anything else like that?
>> Yeah, we are we are looking for people.
It keeps changing. So, I will just go to
musician.com careers. But yeah, it's a
really fun company to work at. So like
helping people learning to play an
instrument, that's a great thing to do.
Yeah.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
joining me. This was great.
>> Thanks a lot.
[music]
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast [music] player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.
>> [music]